我现在宣布你们结为终身伴侣。
I now pronounce you spouses for life.
我说的在经济上帮助他们是认真的。
I meant what I said about helping out, financially.
我有一个同父异母的弟弟。我有一个儿子。
~ I've got a half brother. ~ I've got a son.
我很抱歉。也许我该见见他了。
I am sorry. Perhaps it's time I met him.
西莉亚，跟我说说你的家庭。你真的想嫁给我吗?
~ Celia, tell me about your family. ~ Do you really want to marry me?
我从16岁起就想娶你了。
I've wanted to marry you since I was 16.
你确定吗?~课程!你可以继续工作了。
~ Are you sure about this? ~ Course! You can get on with your work.
我只要半个小时到四十分钟。
I'll only be half an hour, 40 minutes.
发生什么事了?凯特被车撞了。
~ What's happened? ~ Kate's been hit by a car.
你要不要过来一下，我们聊聊天。
Do you want to come through here and we'll have a chat.
菌群。
Flora.
~真的吗?你不喜欢吗?
~ Really? ~ Don't you like it?
这是……这取决于你。
It's... It's up to you.
这不是我们俩的事吗?~是的。当然可以。但是你……你知道的,
~ Isn't it up to both of us? ~ Yes. Of course. But you're... You know,
你在这件事上有更多的发言权。
you've got more say in the matter.
你必须喜欢它。
You've got to like it.
我不讨厌它。
I don't dislike it.
——弗洛拉·格蕾丝~好吧。
~ Flora Grace. ~ OK.
你听起来不怎么激动啊。
You don't sound thrilled.
不，我是。
No, I am.
那你会怎么称呼她?
Well, what would you call her?
我喜欢这个名字。
I like that name.
甜的。好。
Sweet. Good.
所以你不喜欢它。
So you don't like it.
不，我知道，就像我说的。我越来越喜欢它了。这很适合她。
No, I do, like I say. It's growing on me. It suits her.
现在很适合她，但她14岁时还适合吗
Well, it suits her now, but will it suit her when she's 14
然后得到意见。
and got opinions.
我真的很喜欢它。~好吧，这才是最重要的。
~ I really like it. ~ Well, then, that's all that matters.
你只是说说而已。我不会那样做的。
~ You're just saying that. ~ I wouldn't do that.
如果我觉得这真的很可恶，我就会这么说。
If I thought it was really abhorrent, I'd say so.
~相对于轻微的憎恶?~凯特。我们叫她弗洛拉。菌群。
~ As opposed to mildly abhorrent? ~ Kate. We're calling her Flora. Flora.
植物恩典。
Flora Grace.
当然，有一种人造黄油叫Flora。
There is some margarine called Flora, of course.
你现在让我扫兴了。
You've put me off it now.
不，我没有。
No, I haven't.
别那样跟我说话。男人就是这么说话的。
Don't talk to me like that. That's how men talk.
~所以你喜欢格蕾丝?~我喜欢弗洛拉。
~ So you do like Grace? ~ I like Flora.
你真的不知道。很明显。
You really don't. It's obvious.
她是你的孩子。
She's your baby.
她是我们的孩子。
She's our baby.
敲门
KNOCK ON DOOR
妈妈?
Mum?
灵车来了。
The hearse has arrived.
外面的。
It's outside.
正确的。
Right.
你想让我把孩子带走吗?
Do you want me to take the baby?
不,我……
No, I'll...
谢谢。
Thanks.
每件事都有一个季节
To everything there is a season
这是实现世间一切目的的时刻。
and a time to every purpose on earth.
出生的时候，死亡的时候。
A time to be born and a time to die.
在这最后一幕中，
Here in this last act,
悲伤但无所畏惧，
in sorrow but without fear,
在爱和感激中，
in love and appreciation,
我们提交凯瑟琳·艾比克·麦肯齐-道森
we commit Katherine Abike McKenzie-Dawson
到一个自然的结局。
to a natural end.
小女孩。小甜心。
Little girl. Little sweetheart.
你得给这个孩子取个名字。
You are going to have to decide on a name for this baby.
菌群。
Flora.
我在出发前就决定了。
I decided just before we set off.
我是弗洛拉·格蕾丝。
It's Flora Grace.
真漂亮，卡洛琳。
That's beautiful, Caroline.
谢谢你！
Thank you.
吉妮卡，你想不想…
Ginika, do you want to...
那是父亲。不要看。
That's the father. Don't look.
哪一个?
Which one?
矮胖的，苍白的，脸上有毛，12点钟方向。
Pudgy, pale, face hair, 12 o'clock.
一直朝这边看。
Keeps looking this way.
以前叫格雷格。
Used to be called Greg.
可能现在也是。
Probably still is.
他是个白痴。
He's an idiot.
他们经常是。
They often are.
这是另一个。
And here's another one.
约翰。你见过凯特的母亲吉妮卡吗?
John. Have you met Ginika, Kate's mother?
她是经济学教授。
She's a professor of economics.
~啊!~在哥伦比亚大学。
~ Ah! ~ At Columbia.
天哪，你好!
Gosh, how do you do?
可怕的，悲惨的，可怕的情况。
Terrible, tragic, awful situation.
我在约克大学讲英语。
I lecture in English at the University of York.
不要和加拿大的约克大学搞混了，
Not to be confused with York University, which is in Canada,
显然。
apparently.
你已经飞来了?不，她上了蒸汽包。
~ So you've flown in? ~ No, she got on a steam packet.
你是卡罗琳的前任?
You're Caroline's ex?
你一定伤心欲绝。我很抱歉。
You must be devastated, heart-broken. I'm so sorry.
你写小说?
You write novels?
嗯,是的。我已经出版了一两本。
Well, yes. I've published one or two.
杰克·普罗瑟罗，私家侦探，迷失灵魂。
Jack Protheroe, private detective, lost soul.
是的!你已经……你读过……
Yes! You've... Have you read...
哦，很久以前了。
Oh, a long time ago.
我最喜欢的是《闹鬼的人》。
My favourite is The Haunted Man.
它很有趣，很有趣，很有见地。你很聪明。
It's entertaining, it's interesting, it's insightful. You're very clever.
~天哪，嗯，那是……~爸爸?爸爸!
~ Gosh, well, that's... ~ Dad? Dad!
你得挪一下你的车。你把别人挡在里面了。
You need to move your car. You've blocked someone in.
她把手提包落在火葬场了。
She's left her handbag at the crematorium.
你能失陪一下吗?~肯定。
~ Would you excuse me? ~ Sure.
那会让他很开心的。
That'll have made his day.
你不喜欢他。
You don't like him.
我不喜欢凯特的丈夫理查德。
I didn't like Kate's husband, Richard.
我母亲不喜欢我的第一任丈夫，
My mother didn't like my first husband,
道格拉斯，那个患老年痴呆症的人。
Douglas, the one with Alzheimer's.
也许这很正常。也许这是一件事。
Maybe it's normal. Maybe it's a thing.
你母亲喜欢你的第一任丈夫吗?
Did your mother like your first husband?
肯尼斯?
Kenneth?
她把他想得神魂颠倒，
She thought the world of him,
但如果她知道我对他的了解就不会这么做了
but she wouldn't have done if she had known the things I knew about him.
我喜欢卡洛琳。
I like Caroline.
我很喜欢凯特。
I was very fond of Kate.
有时晚上她会过来和我玩拼字游戏，
She'd come round and play Scrabble with me sometimes in the evening,
当我独自一人的时候
when I was on my own.
一开始我觉得很难，
I found it difficult at first,
我并不总是那么善良，但是…
and I wasn't always as kind as I might have been, but...
这是一个惊喜。嗯，说实话，不完全是这样。
~ It was a surprise. ~ Well, not entirely, if I'm being honest.
凯特很高兴
Kate was very happy
卡洛琳。
with Caroline.
大多数时候。~我知道。
~ Most of the time. ~ I know.
弗洛拉·格蕾丝。
So, Flora Grace.
我知道凯特肯定会喜欢的。
Well, I know for a fact Kate would've liked that.
你好。对不起。
Hello. Sorry.
我知道我们合不来，
I know we didn't hit it off,
但我不能不来。
but I couldn't not come.
除了别的，我们是大学朋友，所以…
We were college buddies, apart from anything else, so...
怎么样……我知道我不该问…
How's... I know I'm not supposed to ask...
~ . .孩子怎么样了?她很好。
~ .. but how's the baby? ~ She's fine.
她很好。
She's fine.
~女孩?~是的。
~ A girl? ~ Yes.
我不能看她一眼，对吧?
I couldn't have a look at her, could I?
这不是计划，是吗?~没有。
~ That wasn't the plan, was it? ~ No.
~她会怎么样?她会没事的。
~ What's going to happen to her? ~ She's going to be fine.
~你是…我在照顾她。
~ Are you... ~ I'm looking after her.
~那是……~官方?是的。
~ Is that... ~ Official? Yes.
出生证明上我是她的父亲。
I'm on the birth certificate as her parent.
不，我是想说，这是你想要的吗?
No, I was going to say, is that what you want?
是的。当然是。
Yes. Of course it is.
一定很辛苦。
It must be tough.
我是说，这不是你以为你相信的，对吧?
I mean, it's not what you thought you were buying into, is it?
你不想让她生孩子现在就剩你一个人了。
You didn't want her to have a baby and now you're the one left with it.
我不是不想让她生孩子。
Well, I didn't not want her to have a baby.
对不起，我一定是误解了。
Sorry, I must've misunderstood.
我想要她想要的。
I wanted what she wanted.
她说你不像她那么热心。
She said you weren't as keen as she was.
我没有，但我也不会阻止她。
I wasn't, but I wouldn't have stopped her.
我很抱歉。
I'm sorry.
我得走了。我得搭回曼彻斯特的火车。
I'd better go. I've got to get the train back to Manchester.
我只是…
I just...
我只想说，
I wanted just to say,
看得出来你得到了很多帮助和支持，
I can see you've got a lot of help and support,
但是，如果你只是想找人照顾她一会儿或者……
but, if you just wanted someone to look after her for a bit or...
就像我说的，在其他情况下
And, as I say, under any other circumstances
我不会提供的。我早就退让了。
I wouldn't be offering. I'd have backed off.
我就不会在这里了。这是约定，我很清楚，
I wouldn't even be here. That was the deal and I'm aware of that,
但是，如果有什么，
but, if ever there was anything,
我很灵活，我是自由职业者，我可以在任何地方工作，
I'm flexible, I'm self-employed, I can work anywhere,
所以我不想让你觉得你不能开口
so I wouldn't want you to feel like you couldn't ask
或者它会带来不便，因为很可能它不会带来不便。
or that it'd be inconvenient, because chances are it wouldn't be.
~就这些。~好吧。
~ That's all. ~ OK.
好的，谢谢你。
Well, thank you.
有你…你有我的电话号码吗?
Have you... Have you got my number?
它……
It...
会发到凯特的手机上。
It'll be on Kate's phone.
嗯…
Well...
她在厨房里
She's in the kitchen
和我妈妈或者凯特的妈妈一起，如果你愿意的话
with my mum or Kate's mum if you want to
看看她。
have a look at her.
我不该问的。
I shouldn't have asked.
这取决于你。
It's up to you.
好的。
OK.
问题是，她和凯特的妈妈在一起
Thing is, she's with Kate's mother
凯特的妈妈觉得我是个白痴
and Kate's mother thinks I'm an idiot.
一茶匙发酵粉，一勺牛奶，
A teaspoonful of baking powder, a splash of milk,
一滴香草精就万事大吉了。
a drop of vanilla essence and bob's your uncle.
妈妈。Ginika。
Mum. Ginika.
我是格雷格。~你好。
~ This is Greg. ~ Hi.
格雷格的…
Greg's the...
植物的生物……
Flora's biological...
你好，麦肯齐太太。
Hi, Mrs McKenzie.
我已经二十年不做麦肯齐太太了，格雷格。
I haven't been Mrs McKenzie in 20 years, Greg.
当然可以。离婚了。天啊。
Of course. Divorced. Gosh.
格雷格想……
Greg wanted to...
~扶着她的头。~是的。
~ Support her head. ~ Yeah.
是的。
Yeah.
好的。
OK.
你看到艾伦了吗?
Have you seen Alan?
艾伦吗?
Alan?
他到花园里去和我的数学主任抽烟了。
He went into the garden to have a cigarette with my Head of Maths.
艾伦不抽烟。
Alan doesn't smoke.
~没有。我不知道克里斯也有。你就让他这么做了?
~ No. I didn't know Chris did either. ~ And you just let him?
他有心脏病。
He has a heart condition.
哇。
Wow.
当然，从那以后他们修建了M6收费公路，
Course they've built the M6 toll road since then,
所以我不知道这样是否更有效率。
so I've no idea if that's any more efficient.
哦,狗屎!
Oh, shit!
你在抽烟吗?~没有。
~ Are you smoking? ~ No.
你在抽烟。~我没有。
~ You were smoking. ~ I weren't.
不然你为什么还站在外面下毛毛雨?
Why else would you be standing out here in the drizzle?
我只是…
I just...
你知道他有心脏病吗?
Did you know he has a heart condition?
我是克里斯。~你好。
~ This is Chris. ~ Hi.
你以为数学家会更清楚。
You'd think a mathematician would know better.
我可以解雇你。
I could have you sacked.
给一个有心脏病的人香烟。
Giving cigarettes to a man with a heart condition.
是的，我是卡罗琳的妈妈。
Yes, I'm Caroline's mother.
只有一个。
It were only the one.
我不知道你抽烟。~我不喜欢。我以前是这样。
~ I didn't know you smoked. ~ I don't. I used to.
我现在只是喜欢偶尔来一次。每一个…
I just like the very occasional one now. Every...
我上次吃的是千禧年的。那是什么时候的事?
Look, last one I had were millennium. Now, when were that?
我以为我认识你。~你有。
~ I thought I knew you. ~ You do.
女性,香烟……
Women, cigarettes...
如果我开始抽烟，你觉得怎么样?~我不会。
~ How would you like it if I started smoking? ~ I wouldn't.
哦，那我想我会的。
Oh, then I think I might.
我能抽根烟吗，克里斯?~肯定。
~ Can I have a cigarette, Chris? ~ Sure.
看看你喜欢不喜欢。
See how you like it.
你不需要抽烟来证明你的观点。
You don't have to smoke a cigarette to prove a point.
在葬礼上也一样。
And at a funeral, as well.
你打算让它掉下去吗?
Are you going to let this drop?
好了。
There you go.
我想我还是回去吧。
I think I might go back inside.
别让我阻止你。我不想要你的香烟。
Don't let me stop you. I don't want your cigarettes.
好吧，我…
Right, well, I'll...
嘿，让我露脸!~你想要出现!
~ 'Ere, showing me up! ~ You want showing up!
那只是因为我在乎你。
It's only because I care about you.
这不过是想呼吸点新鲜空气的借口。
It were only an excuse to get a bit of fresh air.
说真的，你抽烟吗?
Seriously, do you smoke?
不!
No!
不。
No.
你想吃果子露吗?
Do you fancy a sherbet?
你没事吧?
You all right?
这些人有一半我都不认识。
I don't know who half these people are.
他们没有参加婚礼。
They weren't at the wedding.
请注意，我们没有邀请很多人来参加婚礼。~没有。
~ Mind you, we didn't invite very many people to the wedding. ~ No.
嗯，我们非正式地邀请了，但大多数人都来不了。
Well, we did, unofficially, but most of them couldn't come.
不，我很抱歉。我们很忙。
No, well, I'm sorry. We were busy.
不管。这都是最后一刻才决定的。
No matter. It was all a bit last minute.
我们这么做是为了她，真的。
We only did it for her, really.
他是孩子的父亲。
He's the father.
生父。
The biological father.
吉妮卡是祖母。
And Ginika's the grandmother.
生物……
The biological...
凯特的妈妈。
Kate's mum.
其实我什么都不是。
And I'm not actually anything.
她得了疝气。天啊，你不需要那个。
~ She's got colic. ~ Jesus, you don't need that.
她现在看起来还好。
She seems OK at the minute.
你等到6点钟。
You wait till six o' clock.
就像按开关一样
It's like flicking a switch
然后一直持续到
and then it can go on till about
凌晨三点。这是可怕的。这就像……
three o'clock in the morning. It's terrible. It's like...
她好像在哭她妈妈，我知道她是疝气，
It's like she's crying for her mother, and I know it's colic,
但这就是我的感觉。
but that's what it feels like.
婴儿的哭声
BABY CRIES
Shush-shush-shush。
Shush-shush-shush.
它只会哭泣。
All it does is cry.
一直持续到凌晨三四点钟，
It goes on till three or four o'clock in the morning,
除此之外你什么都做不了。
and you can't do anything else.
你不能把注意力集中在其他事情上，这很荒谬。
You can't concentrate on anything else and it's ridiculous.
~是的，不，这是…一定是。是啊，对妈妈来说更糟。
~ Yeah, no, it's... It must be. ~ Yeah, well, it's worse for Mum.
不，不是。她想要。
No, it isn't. She wanted it.
我都不知道这是干什么用的。它是做什么的?
I don't even know what it's for. What does it do?
它只是哭泣和拉屎。
It just cries and shits.
~ Oi !Oi !那就行了。
~ Oi! Oi! ~ That'll do.
这都不是我们的，而你又不在这里，所以闭嘴。
It's not even ours, and you're not even here, so shut up.
是啊，你已经长大了，可以开始帮助她，支持她了，
Yeah, and you're old enough to start trying to help her and support her,
而不是像个以自我为中心的小混蛋
instead of behaving like a self-centred little dick
~一直都是。滚开。哦，你滚开。
~ all the time. ~ Piss off. ~ Oh, you piss off.
停止它!
Stop it!
没有你，妈妈的事已经够多了……
Mum's got enough on her plate without you...
我以为你在躺着呢。
I thought you were having a lie down.
是的，但是我睡不着，所以…~她很好!她很好!
~ Yeah, but I couldn't sleep, so... ~ She's fine! She's fine!
我要带她出去呼吸点新鲜空气。
I'm just going to take her out for a bit of fresh air.
不，你不需要。~我想!我们相爱了。我们保税。
~ No, you don't have to. ~ I want to! We're in love. We've bonded.
手了。
Hands off.
开车。这对疝气宝宝有好处。
Driving. That's meant to be good for colicky babies.
她有什么东西可以裹起来吗?
Has she got something I can wrap her up in?
是的，她有一件可爱的粉色丝绒小外套和一顶相配的帽子
Yes, she's got a lovely little pink velour coat and a matching hat
艾伦和我给她买的
that Alan and me bought her.
是振动和声音。
It's the vibration and the sound.
就像在子宫里一样。
It's like being in the womb.
显然，这都是DH劳伦斯的风格。
Obviously, it's all very DH Lawrence.
婴儿车在走廊里，亲爱的，还有条毯子。
The pushchair's in the hall, love, and there's a blanket.
我一个小时左右回来。
I'll be an hour or so.
~你休息一下。~谢谢。
~ You get some rest. ~ Thanks.
我得坐下了。
I'm going to have to sit down.
我已经尽力了。
I've done what I can.
艾伦，你进去吧。我给你拿点茶来。
Oh, Alan, you go in there. I'll bring you some tea.
你还好吗，亲爱的?
Are you all right, love?
是的。
Yeah.
凯特的妈妈在哪里?
Where's Kate's mum?
~我想她也在躺着休息。她还好吗?
~ She's having a lie down, as well, I think. ~ Is she all right?
不，她当然不是。这是不可能发生的，不是吗?
No, of course she's not. It's not meant to happen, is it?
你的一个孩子走在你前面。
One of your children going before you.
他无法忍受哭泣。
He can't stand it, the crying.
我也不能。
I can't either.
我们还知道发生了什么吗
Do we know any more about what's happened
对那些把她撞倒的白痴吗?
to the idiots that knocked her down?
我没告诉你吗?
Oh, did I not tell you?
你说有偷车的指控，
Well, you said there were charges of car theft,
鲁莽驾驶和过失杀人。
reckless driving and manslaughter.
他们被保释，
They were released on bail,
~前天。~不!
~ day before yesterday. ~ No!
当我说我们应该恢复绞刑时，你嘲笑我。
And you laugh at me when I say we should bring back hanging.
我去看看劳伦斯怎么样了。
I'll go and see if Lawrence is all right.
你去和艾伦一起坐进去。
You go and sit down in there with Alan.
我给你们俩拿点茶来。你确定?
~ I'll bring you both some tea. ~ You sure?
是的，继续。滚吧。
Yeah, go on. Off you pop.
一会儿见。
See you in a bit.
那里有一条茶巾。
There's a tea towel there.
是的。事实上，我可能也会出去呼吸点新鲜空气。
Yeah. Actually, I might pop out and get a bit of fresh air, as well.
你是透明的。你知道的，不是吗?
You're transparent. You do know that, don't you?
妈妈在泡茶。
Mum's making the tea.
她撞见我抽烟。
She caught me smoking.
啊，那是我的错。
Ah, that was my fault.
所以我又有麻烦了。
So I'm in bother again.
我很高兴你克服了……
I'm glad you got over that...
. .另一件事。
.. other thing.
我不太确定我们有。
I'm not entirely sure we have.
我想它被搁置了。
I think it's been put on hold.
那里没有别的骷髅了，是吗，
And there are no other skeletons, are there,
在橱柜里?
in the cupboard?
我知道这不关我的事，但她是我妈妈。
I know it's none of my business, but she's my mum.
不。
No.
没有骷髅了。我不像你爸爸。
No more skeletons. I weren't like your dad.
好吧,
Well,
除了,
except,
~我想知道我是不是。你是什么意思?
~ I wonder if I were. ~ What do you mean?
不是……不是不同的女人，只是…
Not... Not different women, just...
我确实爱过艾琳……
I did love Eileen...
. .但随后，一个缓慢的、初见端倪的意识出现了
.. but, then, a slow, dawning realisation
你已经接受了这样的事情
that you've settled for summat that
你一直都知道这不是你想要的。
you knew all along weren't really what you wanted.
当她怀上吉莉安的时候，
When she became pregnant with Gillian,
我以为这是我想要的，但是，
I thought it were what I wanted, but,
事实上，它吓到我了。
actually, it frightened me.
我很高兴，但是
Delighted me, but
吓到我了，“就这样了吗?”
frightened me, like, "Is this it?"
我很抱歉。我听起来像是在找借口，
I'm sorry. I'm sounding like I'm making excuses,
但是，没有，再也没有发生过，所以…
but, no, it never happened again, so...
对不起。对不起。
Sorry. Sorry.
我不该说这些的。不是现在。
I shouldn't have started talking about that. Not now.
我爸爸也不全是坏人。
He wasn't all bad, my dad.
不。
No.
好吧，谁想当妈妈?
Right, who wants to be mother?
你做的事情。
You do.
我撞见他抽烟。我告诉过你吗?
I caught him smoking. Did I tell you?
是的，是我……我很抱歉。
Yes, it was me that... I'm sorry.
你为什么向他道歉?
What're you apologising to him for?
他是76年!如果他连一小根烟都不能抽
He's 76! If he can't have one single tiny cigarette
不会让你觉得自己像个六岁小孩。
without being made to feel like a six-year-old.
接下来我们会发现他一直在为俄罗斯人做间谍。
We'll find out he's been spying for the Russians next.
我们都有缺点，不是吗?
Well, we've all got our shortcomings, haven't we?
他抽烟，你看每日邮报。
He smokes, you read the Daily Mail.
我不抽烟!
I don't smoke!
只在电视上播放。
Only for the telly page.
当然，你很完美，不是吗?~伊什。
~ Of course, you're perfect, aren't you. ~ Ish.
给你，亲爱的。
There you go, love.
约翰去找吉莉安了。
John's gone after Gillian.
我告诉他，我说"你是透明的"
I told him, I said, "You're transparent."
对不起。嗨。
Sorry. Hi.
是的，我知道。
Yeah, I know.
可预测、无聊、透明。
Predictable, boring, transparent.
最近怎么样?~好。
~ How're things? ~ Fine.
好。好。
Good. Good.
我想…
I wanted to...
我知道这很难
Look, I know this is difficult,
尴尬的,
it's awkward,
但是，你知道，我们是成年人。
but, you know, we're adults.
~我们可以…我和Robbie要结婚了。
~ We can... ~ Me and Robbie's getting married.
我告诉过你他邀请过我，现在我答应了。
I told you he'd asked me, and now I've said yes.
我两周前就答应了
I said yes two weeks ago,
只是我们还没告诉任何人。
only we've not told anyone yet.
我们只是想等到葬礼结束后再正式宣布。
We were just waiting until after the funeral to announce it properly.
所以你是第一个知道的。
So you're the first to know.
好的。好吧,这是
OK. Well, that's
好。
good.
这是……
That's...
的东西……
The thing...
我想说的是，考虑到凯特的事，
The thing I wanted to say was that, given what's happened with Kate,
我想她需要我在这里。
I think she needs me here.
卡洛琳。
Caroline.
我觉得她可能需要我陪着劳伦斯，
I think she needs me here for Lawrence, probably,
所以我……很显然……
so I... Obviously...
我向你提供农场的经济援助，就像我做的那样，
Me offering you financial help with the farm, as I did,
~可能有些事我不能……很好。
~ might be something that I can't... ~ That's fine.
~不能再做了。很好。
~ Can't do any more. ~ That's fine.
~不过，如果你要嫁给Robbie…是的，很好。
~ Still, if you're marrying Robbie... ~ Yes, it's fine.
你确定他…~是的。
~ Are you sure he's... ~ Yes.
~ . .你真的想要什么?是的，我是。
~ .. really what you want? ~ Yes, I am.
好。
Good.
反正我也没把它当回事。~不是吗?
~ I didn't take it very seriously anyway. ~ No?
不。好。
No. Good.
好了，这就是我想说的。为某事感谢~肯定。
~ Well, that's all I wanted to say. Thank you for... ~ Sure.
~ . .如此善解人意。没有问题。
~ .. being so understanding. ~ It's no problem.
我确实认为这是个错误。
I do think it's a mistake.
Robbie。
Robbie.
我不在乎你怎么想。~他太……
~ I don't care what you think. ~ He's so...
不。
No.
不，我想你不知道。
No, I don't suppose you do.
我们还没告诉任何人，我们结婚的事。
We haven't told anyone, yet, about us getting married.
和凯特在一起。
What with Kate.
所以不要再重复了。
So don't go repeating it.
门打开
DOOR OPENS
信不信由你，她睡着了。
She's asleep, believe it or not.
我不知道要多久。
I don't know how long for.
我把她留在婴儿车里了。
I've left her in her pram.
谢谢。
Thanks.
她是个可爱的孩子。
She's a sweet baby.
我是说，当她不尖叫的时候…
I mean, when she's not screaming blue mur...
尖叫得要命。
Screaming her head off.
你不这么认为吗?
Do you not think?
我想我更喜欢他们15岁左右的样子。
I think I prefer them when they get to be about 15.
大家都走了吗?
Has everyone gone?
妈妈和艾伦在隔壁。
Mum and Alan are next door.
他们会在电视机前睡觉，凯特的妈妈在床上。
They'll be asleep in front of the telly and Kate's mum's in bed.
可怜的女人。
Poor woman.
毫米。
Mm.
可怜的你。
Poor you.
~我最好自己去录。~肯定。
~ I'd better be making tracks myself. ~ Sure.
听着，我想跟你说点事。
Listen, I wanted to talk to you about something.
现在可能不是时候
Now might not be the time,
但我不想让你从我爸爸或你妈妈那里听到
but I don't want you to hear it from my dad or your mum
你可能会误解别人的意思。~好吧。
~ and get the wrong end of the stick. ~ OK.
我开始…
I've started...
我又和Robbie约会了
I've been seeing Robbie again,
我知道。我知道你觉得这不好
and I know. I know you think that's bad,
考虑到……
given what...
我告诉你的事
The thing I told you,
但他对我有好处，他是我的真命天子，他让我不再当傻瓜，
but he's good for me, he's right for me, he stops me being a pillock,
现在他向我求婚，我答应了
and now he's asked me to marry him and I've said yes.
卡洛琳。
Caroline.
我现在不能想那件事。~不，我知道。我只是…
~ I can't think about that now. ~ No, I know. I just...
就像我说的，我不想让你从别人那里听到。
Like I said, I didn't want you hearing it from anyone else.
你脑子里在想什么?
What's going through your head?
什么吗?
Anything?
我不知道。如果你能接受，那是你的事。
I don't know. I guess if you can live with it that's your business.
你能吗?
Can you?
我能做什么?
Can I what?
这样做呢?
Do that?
和某人住在一起，和某人睡觉，了解你
Live with someone, sleep with someone, knowing you
谋杀了他的兄弟?
murdered his brother?
我想我做不到。我想这是我应该避免的。
I don't think I could. I think it's just something I'd avoid.
艾迪让我受够了。
I had a lot to put up with with Eddie.
我做了…
I did exp...
我确实告诉过你。
I did tell you that.
是的，我知道。
Yes, I know.
我喜欢Robbie。我一直很喜欢Robbie。
I like Robbie. I've always liked Robbie.
他喜欢我。
He likes me.
他爱我。
He loves me.
我应该嫁的是他
It's him I should've married,
那么多年以前，这一切都不可能…
all those years ago, and none of this would ever've...
对不起，我现在不能考虑这个问题。
I'm sorry, I can't think about it now.
不。确定。
No. Sure.
你知道吗，那天晚上，你就是那个，
You know, you were the one, that night,
说这就是为什么你和罗比永远不可能是个好主意。
saying that's why it could never be a good idea, you and Robbie.
我第二天说的话，我只是同意你的观点。
What I said the next day, I was just agreeing with you.
我不记得了。
I have no memory of that.
没有，但是
Well, no, but
你所做的。
you did.
是啊，他邀请我了，我答应了。
Yeah, well, he's asked me and I've said yes.
我不能……我不能再让他失望了。
I can't... I can't let him down again.
我记得我们说过要假装的
I thought we said we were going to pretend
你从没跟我说过埃迪的事。
you never told me about Eddie.
是的。是的，我们做到了。
Yeah. Yeah, we did.
那好吧。
All right, then.
~对吧。~所以…
~ Right. ~ So...
你喜欢做什么就做什么。你做你觉得舒服的事。
You do what you like. You do what you feel comfortable with.
好像我需要你的许可似的。
Like I need your permission.
婴儿的哭声
BABY CRIES
角哔哔声
HORN BEEPS
早....
Morning.
你好。
Hiya.
怎么样?
How was it?
卡罗琳怎么样?
How was Caroline?
安静。累了。
Quiet. Tired.
我不知道你为什么不让我跟你一起去。
I don't know why you wouldn't let me come with you.
可爱的小宝贝。
Sweet little baby.
如此悲伤，如此令人心碎。
So sad, so heartbreaking.
那个没用的油乎乎的家伙在那儿吗?
Was that feckless streak of oily shite there?
哦,约翰。对，对，对。
Oh, John. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
所以，还好你没去。
So, probably good job you weren't there.
你跟他谈过了吗?
Did you talk to him?
不。
No.
没有必要了。
No longer than necessary.
你能想象去找你前妻的女朋友…
Can you imagine going to your ex-wife's girlfriend...
合作伙伴的葬礼吗?
Partner's funeral?
他只是……他没有……
He's just... He's got no...
我不知道。
I don't know.
礼仪。
Decorum.
是的。你知道中产阶级是什么样的。
Yeah. Well, you know what middle-class people are like.
他们闹翻了，离婚了，然后他们还在说话
They fall out and get divorced, then they're still speaking to each other
只是为了显示他们都长大了。
just to show how grown-up they all are.
旋钮。
Knob.
是的。
Yup.
但她没事吧?卡洛琳?
But she were all right? Caroline?
她得了疝气。
She's got colic.
婴儿。菌群。
The baby. Flora.
最重要的是，她太累了。
So, on top of everything else, she's just exhausted.
昨天这里一切都好吗?
Was everything all right here, yesterday?
是啊，说实话，我没怎么见过他们。
Yeah, I didn't see much of 'em, to be honest.
大家又在加里家呆了一整天
Raff were over at Gary's place all day again
Ellie把Calamity带到她妈妈家。
and Ellie took Calamity to her mother's.
我不知道那是怎么回事。
I've no idea how that went.
我看着羊，然后被叫去加班，
I saw to t'sheep, then I got called in for some of overtime,
我得去掩护一个3 - 10，所以…
I had to cover a three-ten, so...
我们要告诉他们吗?关于我们?
Are we going to tell 'em? About us?
你说过在我葬礼之后。
You said after t'funeral.
是的。
Yep.
所以,今天好吗?
So, today?
今天。
Today.
然后我们需要开始思考我们要做的是什么。
Then we need to start thinking about what sort of do we're having.
和在哪里。还有我们邀请的人。
And where. And who we're inviting.
你觉得我们的预算是多少?
What sort of budget d'you think we're looking at?
因为你知道我有…非常小。
Cos you know I've got... very little.
我是说，我爸可能会把手伸进口袋，但是…
I mean, me dad might stick his hand in his pocket, but...
~还有你的Gary。我没有向加里要任何东西。
~ And your Gary. ~ I'm not asking Gary, for anything.
我才认识他五分钟!
I've only known him five minutes!
我在开玩笑!
I'm joking!
拉夫昨天跟他相处得怎么样?
How did Raff get on with him yesterday?
伟大的时间,
Great time,
阳光从他的裤子里照出来。
sun shines out of his trousers.
加里就是上帝。这是官方的。
Gary is God. It's official.
嗯…登记处，不是教堂。
Erm... Registry Office, not church.
然后我们就可以在sportsman餐厅吃烤猪了。
Then we can have, like, an hog roast up at t'Sportsman's.
比如烧烤和自助餐。我们可以弄个帐篷。
Like, a barbecue and a buffet. We could get a marquee.
稳定。
Steady on.
~还有乐队。~什么样的乐队?
~ And a band. ~ What sort of band?
好吧，反正是个DJ。
Well, a DJ, anyway.
我们会考虑的。~还有蜜月!
~ We'll think about it. ~ And a honeymoon!
我们一定要去度蜜月。
We're definitely going on honeymoon.
两个星期。整整两个星期。
And for two weeks. Two whole weeks.
更长时间。
Longer.
我们为什么不买四个呢?
Why don't we go for four?
四个星期。一个非常令人兴奋的地方，比如……
Four weeks. Somewhere really exciting, like...
澳大利亚。你可以去见见你所有的表兄妹!
Australia. You could go and meet all your cousins!
~是的。他可以照看他的羊。
~ Yeah. ~ He can look after t'sheep.
~谁能?你可以的。~什么时候?
~ Who can? ~ You can. ~ When?
当我和你妈妈去度蜜月的时候。
When me and your mum go off on us honeymoon.
罗比向我求婚了
Robbie's asked me to marry him and...
我答应了。
I've said yes.
~真的吗?~是的。
~ Really? ~ Yeah.
不，真的吗?~是的。
~ No, really? ~ Yeah.
不,严重吗?
No, seriously?
是的!
Yes!
祝你好运，伙计。~闭嘴!
~ Good luck, buddy. ~ Shut up!
不，不错。你可能需要检查一下脑袋，但是……
No, nice one. You probably need your head examined but...
你会……吗?~我开玩笑的!
~ Will you...? ~ I'm joking!
好吧，我不是。恭喜你!什么时候?
Well, I'm not. Congratulations! When?
~很快。你是在邀请同事吗?喜欢的,嗯…
~ Soon as. ~ Are you inviting people from work? Like, erm...
除了谢丽尔，所有人都是。
Well, everybody except Cheryl, yeah.
我们不能在家里提这个名字，谢谢。
We don't mention that name in this house, thank you.
哇哇哇!
Aww!
你们俩都疯了。但是…
You're mad, both of you. But...
. .我为你感到高兴。
.. I'm very happy for you.
加里说你为什么不给他打电话?
Oh, Gary says why haven't you rang him?
~给他打电话。我就是这么说的。他以为你和他闹翻了。
~ Rung him. ~ That's what I said. He thinks you've fell out with him.
和他闹翻了。为什么?
Fallen out with him. Why?
~是的，你和我~爷爷。为什么?~我不知道。他为什么这么想?
~ Yeah, you and me ~ Grandad. Why? ~ I don't know. ~ Why's he think that?
我只是传个话。
I'm just passing a message.
过几分钟我就过来看看她过得怎么样了。
I'll pop round in a few minutes and see how she's getting on.
毫米。
Mm.
~手机震动~哦，是我。
~ MOBILE PHONE VIBRATES ~ Ooh, that's me.
“嗨,爷爷。猜猜看。
"Hi, Grandad. Guess what.
“妈妈和罗比叔叔要结婚了。
"Mum and Uncle Robbie are getting married.
“你知道吗?”不，我当然没有!
"Did you know?" No, I damn well didn't!
“她一定是叫那个混蛋滚开了。”
"She must have told that John tosser to eff off."
“我希望卡罗琳没事。加里说你为什么不给他打电话。
"I hope Caroline is OK. Gary says why haven't you rang him.
“爱废料”。
"Love Raff".
~结婚了。~好吧，好吧!
~ Married. ~ Well, well!
我会尽我所能帮你。好吗?但这真的很有帮助
I will do everything I can for you. OK? But it would really help
如果你能在晚上停止哭泣。
if you could stop doing all this crying at night.
我知道你忍不住，我也知道你根本不知道我在说什么。
I know you can't help it, and I know you haven't a clue what I'm talking about.
她叹了口气
SHE SIGHS
你妈妈会为你高兴的。
Your mum would've been so thrilled with you.
用你的每一点一滴。
With every tiny, tiny little bit of you.
对吧,…
Right, well,...
. .我们有很多选择。
.. we've got options.
如果我说什么你喜欢的话就打断我。
Just interrupt me if I say anything you like the sound of.
一个，这是一个大问题……
One, and this is a big one,...
. .我要提前退休。
.. is that I take early retirement.
我可能得把这里卖了，
I'd have to sell this place, probably,
但从好的方面来说，我有一笔不小的退休金。
but, on the plus side, I've got a not insubstantial pension going on.
我是一个聪明的人。你很快就会习惯的。
I am nothing if not a smart cookie. You'll soon get used to that.
这个计划的缺陷是我仍然……
The flaw in that plan is that I am still...
不是没有野心……
not without ambition...
. .在过去的职业部门…
.. in the old career department...
. .这就引出了第二个选择。
.. which brings me onto option number two.
我们要求其他人参与并帮助我们。
We ask other people to get involved and help out.
我的母亲。
My mother.
我的母亲。你见过我妈妈吗?
My mother. Have you met my mother?
哦，还有约翰。你见过约翰了。好几次了。
Oh, and then there's John. The ex. You have met John. Several times.
他就是那天喋喋不休谈论拉迪亚德·吉卜林的人
He's the one who was going on about Rudyard Kipling the other day
当时我正试图精神崩溃。他是个白痴。
when I was trying to have a nervous breakdown. He's an idiot.
他不是白痴，他只是个普通人
Well, he's not an idiot, he's just someone
他从来都不知道如何成为一个成年人，
who never got the hang of being one of the grown-ups,
你可以说这是他魅力的一部分，也可以说不是。
which you could say is part of his charm, or not.
但是,
But,
我另外两个孩子小的时候，他和他们相处得很好。
he was very good with my other two when they were little.
好吧，他是又不是。
Well, he was and he wasn't.
当然，还有保姆的选择。
And, then, of course, there's always the nanny option.
但我知道你妈妈会怎么想。
But I know what your mum'd think about that.
这是不可能的。
That's not happening.
是啊，她会讨厌的。
Yeah, she'd hate it.
她会说"这不是计划的一部分"
She'd say, "That was never part of the plan."
嗯，它不是。~不，我知道。
~ Well, it wasn't. ~ No, I know.
但你不在这里也不是计划的一部分，对吧?
But you not being here wasn't part of the plan either, was it?
她在自言自语。她在跟孩子说话呢，你个笨蛋。
~ She's talking to herself. ~ She's talking to the baby, you knob.
这就是牛津大学教你的语言吗?
Is that the sort of language they teach you at Oxford?
嗯，他是个讨厌鬼。你真是个笨蛋。~旋钮。
~ Well, he is a knob. ~ You're a knob. ~ Knob.
凯特的妈妈醒了吗?~旋钮。~没见过她。
~ Is Kate's mum up? ~ Knob. ~ Not seen her.
它又哭了，一直哭到今天凌晨两三点。
It cried again, till like 20 to three this morning.
你试过用耳塞吗?
Have you tried using earplugs?
~你还能听到!~她!
~ You can still hear it! ~ Her!
它甚至不是我们的。他不能再那样说了，奶奶，他会让妈妈难过的。
~ It's not even ours. ~ He's got to stop saying that, Gran, he's going to upset Mum.
她不是别人的，亲爱的。它的爸爸是谁?
~ Well, she's no-one else's, love. ~ Who's its father?
那是……他昨天在这里。
It was that, erm... He was here yesterday.
~哪一个?~高。白脸。
~ Which one? ~ Tall. Pasty-faced.
Ginger-ish。我的胡子有点长了。
Ginger-ish. Got a, like a bit of a beard thing going on.
加文。
Gavin.
~加雷斯。吉尔伯特。~甘道夫?
~ Gareth. Gilbert. ~ Gandalf?
格雷格!格雷格。
Greg! It's Greg.
你绝对想不到他会是凯特的菜。不动。
You'd never think he'd be Kate's sort. Still.
是啊，那他为什么不能接受呢?
Yeah, well, why can't HE take it?
天啊，你还真知道怎么让自己受欢迎啊?
God, you really know how to make yourself popular, don't you?
有人给你妈妈倒杯茶吗?
Has anybody taken your mother a cup of tea?
敲门
KNOCK AT DOOR
我能进来吗?
Can I come in?
你好。
Hello.
婴儿咯咯的笑声
BABY GURGLES
它不会永远持续下去，……
It won't last forever,...
. .感觉就像这样。
.. feeling like this.
我知道你现在很难想象。
I know it's hard for you to imagine that just now.
你什么时候有过这种感觉?
When did you ever feel like this?
~我爸爸去世的时候没有。~不，不。那是我爸爸去世的时候。
~ Not when my dad died. ~ No, no. It was when MY dad died.
我哭了整整一个星期，
I cried for an entire week,
固体。
solid.
我崇拜他走过的土地。
I worshipped the ground he walked on.
59岁。
59 years old.
他已经死了……
He's been dead...
47、48年了。
47, 48 years now.
1966年,
1966,
你出生的那一年。
the year you were born.
我以为我再也笑不出来了。
I thought I would never smile again.
然后……你来了。
And then... you came along.
你和他长得一模一样。
And you looked just like him.
你觉得死了很奇怪吗?
Do you think it's weird, being dead?
我们最终都会知道的，不是吗?
Well, we all get to find out eventually, don't we?
我很怀疑。
I doubt it.
我想一旦你走了，你就走了。
I reckon once you're gone, you're gone.
~我觉得留下来的人更奇怪。~毫米。
~ I think it's more weird for the people left behind. ~ Mm.
你认为有些人逗留的时间更长吗?
Do you think some people linger longer...
比其他的吗?
than others?
我想有时候会有这种感觉。
I suppose it can feel like that sometimes.
我觉得这更多的是你的想象，不是吗，
I think it's more in your imagination, isn't it,
诸如此类的事情?
that sort of thing?
我忍不住……
I can't help...
担心……
worrying...
. .想象着她做了什么，不知道什么时候被撞了……
.. imagining what she did and didn't know when she got hit...
. .她的经历，她的想法，
.. what she went through, what she was thinking,
不管它有多快。
however quick it was.
她一定很害怕
How frightened she must've been,
想知道她到底出了什么事。
wondering what the hell was happening to her.
她是一个如此平和的人
She was such a peaceful person,
她那么冷静，那么善良，然后……
she was so calm, she was so kind, and then...
. .就这样惨死……这太……
.. to die like that so violently... It's just so...
这种事绝对不应该发生在她身上。
Not in a million years is that what should've happened to her.
这很不公平。
It's very unfair.
但我怕，爱情，生活可以很不公平。
But I'm afraid, love, life can be very unfair.
你……
You...
这段时间会很艰难。
It'll be tough for a while.
但你会从另一边出来的。你会的。
But you'll come out the other side. You will.
最终。
Eventually.
你知道你会的。
You know you will.
因为你……
Cos you're...
你有弹性。
You're resilient.
~她抽泣~你很聪明。
~ SHE SOBS ~ You're clever.
她抽泣
SHE SOBS
哦,甜心。
Oh, sweetheart.
你给吉妮卡带茶了吗?
Did you take Ginika some tea?
是的，我做了。她还好吗?
~ Yes, I did. ~ Is she all right?
我想是的。
I think so.
我一直在考虑其他选择。
I've been thinking about options.
我真的不想放弃我的工作，我会怨恨它，
I really don't want to give up my job, I'd resent it,
那对我们俩都不好。
and that wouldn't be good for either of us.
我们中的任何一个。会吗?~没有。~会吗?~没有。
~ Any of us. Would it? ~ No. ~ Would it? ~ No.
我也不能兼职当班主任，只是……
And I can't go part-time as a head teacher, it's just...
~几个月都没有?这对学校不公平。
~ Not even for a few months? ~ It's not fair on the school.
那么，凯特要怎么做呢?
Well, what was Kate going to do?
嗯，她打算休息一年，然后她会回来兼职。更容易……
Well, she was going to take a year off and then she was going to come back part-time. It's easier...
对于教师来说，情况完全不同。问题是……
for teachers, it's completely different. And the thing is...
. .如果我雇保姆，她会不高兴的
.. she'd hate it if I employed a nanny
~而弗洛拉那么小。~毫米。
~ whilst Flora's so tiny. ~ Mm.
所以，事情是……
So, the thing is...
我会尽我所能，亲爱的，为你，
I'll do what I can, love, for you,
但是，你知道，我有世界上最好的意志，我76岁了。
but, you know, with the best will in the world, I'm 76.
我知道。我不是……
I know. I wasn't...
我很抱歉。我没打算让你全职做任何事
I'm sorry. I wasn't going to ask you to do anything full-time
但如果我能权衡几个选择
but if I could balance a few options,
你，你和艾伦，你能…
could you, you and Alan, could you...
我不知道，做一些奇怪的…
I don't know, do the odd...
. .转变?
.. shift?
是的。是的，我们当然可以。
Yes. Yes, of course we could.
吉莉安和罗比要结婚了。我们刚收到一条短信。
Gillian and Robbie are getting married. We've just had a text.
是的，我知道，她昨晚告诉我的。
Yes, I know, she told me last night.
我觉得他对她来说是件好事。
I think he could be a very good thing for her.
她嫁给了他的兄弟。
She was married to his brother.
是啊，也不是没听说过。
Yeah, well, it's not unheard of.
~没有。~是吗?
~ No. ~ Is it?
有什么事吗?
What's up?
你不喜欢她，是吗?~你介意吗?!
~ You don't fancy her, do you? ~ Do you MIND?!
嗯，我只是…我们是朋友!~我知道。正确的。~伊什。
~ Well, I just... ~ We're friends! ~ I know. Right. ~ Ish.
当她不像个傻瓜的时候。
When she's not behaving like a twit.
这么小的人都请保姆了。
People do have nannies from being this tiny.
是的，我知道。
Yeah, I know.
只要找到合适的人就行了。
It'd just be a matter of finding the right person.
~天啊。~直接说不……
~ Gosh. ~ Just say no...
~没有。~ . .如果这是个愚蠢的想法。
~ No. ~ .. if it's a stupid idea.
~不，是……我知道你没有理由要帮我。
~ No, it's... ~ I know you've got no reason to want to help me.
不,这是……
No, it's...
~有趣的。我刚想起来
~ intriguing. ~ It just occurred to me
因为在你输了之后你似乎还想参与…
because you seemed to want to be involved after you lost...
是的。
Yeah.
~朱蒂丝的，还有……~是的。是的。
~ Judith's, and... ~ Yeah. Yeah.
是的。
Yeah.
不，你说得对，这是个蠢主意。
No, you're right, it's a stupid idea.
我不知道我为什么会想到这个。算了吧。
I don't know why I thought of it. Forget it.
我可以……
I could...
也许可以试着帮你。
try and help you out maybe.
一周一个下午。一个小时。左右。
One afternoon a week. For an hour. Or so.
然后如果西莉亚每周来几天。或者更多。
And then if Celia did a couple of days a week. Or more.
~她76岁了。~肯定。确定。
~ She's 76. ~ Sure. Sure.
这不是……
It's not...
这不是凯特想要的。我。是吗?
It's not really what Kate would've wanted. Me. Is it?
我是说，很明显，我很乐意偶尔做些奇怪的……但是…
I mean, obviously, I'd be happy to do the occasional, odd... but...
实际上，一般来说，我不认为……
Realistically, on a regular basis, I don't think...
你还打算在附近买套公寓或别的什么，是吗?
You're still intending to buy a flat or something close by, aren't you?
这样你就能多陪陪劳伦斯了吗?
So you can spend more time with Lawrence?
~肯定。确定。你真的开始找了吗?
~ Sure. Sure. ~ Have you actually started looking?
嗯…不。
Erm... no.
但是我会的
But I will
我会帮你的卡洛琳
and I will help you, Caroline.
我会的，我会尽我所能，我会尽可能多地帮助你。
I will, I'll do what I can, I'll help you out as often as I can.
但是我认为……
But I think...
你必须现实一点。
You've got to be realistic.
你受到了沉重的打击
You've been dealt a terrible blow,
太可怕了，太……
it's awful, it's...
但重点是，
But the point is,
你必须看到这是改变人生的
you have to see that this is life-changing
你不能假装它不是。
and you can't pretend it isn't.
你要么要雇佣一个全职的…
You've either going to have to employ a full-time...
一个知道如何照顾这么小的人的合适人选
proper person who knows how to look after people this tiny
或者放弃你的工作，至少暂时放弃。
or give up your job, at least temporarily.
我不能那样做。我不能放弃我的工作，我会发疯的。
I can't do that. I can't give up my job, I'd go mad.
你要开车送我去车站吗?~肯定。
~ Are you going to drive me to the station? ~ Sure.
~我可以…我来做。
~ I can... ~ I'll do it.
给我打电话，发短信，告诉我你安全回来了。
Ring me, text me, and let me know you've got back safely.
你要照顾好自己。
You look after yourself.
再见,宝贝。
Bye-bye, baby.
她是你妹妹，你知道的，对吧?你会把她当成你的妹妹。
She's your sister, you know that, don't you? You will think of her as your sister.
我当然知道。
Course I do.
我当然会。
Course I will.
~再见。再见，爱。
~ See you. ~ Bye-bye, love.
~现在怎么办?上帝知道。
~ Now what? ~ God knows.
你知道，你做得很好。不，我不是。
~ You're doing really well, you know. ~ No, I'm not.
我想你是。~我在自言自语!
~ I think you are. ~ I'm talking to myself!
这通常是疯狂的表现。
That's usually a sign of madness.
你可以随时给格雷格打电话。
You could always ring Greg.
我不会给格雷格打电话的。他的确提出了。
~ I'm not ringing Greg. ~ He did offer.
我不会给格雷格打电话的。
I'm not ringing Greg.
也许他不像你想的那么傻。
Maybe he isn't as big a twerp as you think he is.
不，我认为作为笨蛋，在笨蛋部门
No, I think as twerps go - in the twerp department -
格雷格太过分了。
Greg goes off the deep end.
你就是不喜欢他。不是吧，夏洛克。
~ You just don't like him. ~ No shit, Sherlock.
不要在弗洛拉面前骂人。~对不起。
~ Don't swear in front of Flora. ~ Sorry.
~反正你用得太多了。你知道的，不是吗?~是的。
~ You over-use that phrase anyway. You know that, don't you? ~ Yup.
你也知道，格雷格
You do realise, as well, that Greg
是这个星球上唯一有可能这么做的人吗
is the only person on the planet who's likely to
像你和我妈妈一样保护弗洛拉。
feel as protective towards Flora as you and my mum do.
我妈妈又有什么用呢?
And what use is my mum going to be?
她将于周二飞回美国。
She's winging it back to the States on Tuesday.
你真的不喜欢我请保姆吗?
Would you really hate it if I got a nanny?
一个好保姆，一个非常好的，昂贵的，合适的保姆。
A good nanny, a really good, expensive, proper nanny.
我不会跟你说话的，卡罗琳。~看…
~ I wouldn't speak to you, Caroline. ~ Look...
你脑子里有《欢乐满人间》那个保姆根本不存在。
You've got Mary Poppins in your head. That nanny doesn't exist.
我来打几个电话。
Let me ring some of those numbers.
我们都可能会感到惊喜。我保证。我保证。
We might both be pleasantly surprised. I promise. I promise.
我不会做任何你讨厌的事。
I won't do anything you'd hate.
看！我也爱这个孩子!
Look! I love this kid too!
没有你想的那么多，但我想。
Not as much as you would've done, but I do.
我爱她，我会为她做我能做的一切!
I love her and I will do everything I can for her!
但我得处理这一切!
But I've got to deal with it all!
是什么让我困惑，妈妈，如果我…~虚伪的。
~ What confuses me though, Mother, if I'm being... ~ Disingenuous.
诚实的。
Honest.
这是什么意思?
What does that mean?
他知道。
He knows.
不到两周前，约翰留下来了。
Is that less than two weeks ago, John stayed.
~是的，但是什么也没发生。他睡在你的房间。
~ Yeah, but nothing happened. ~ He slept in your room.
那并不意味着什么。通常是这样的。
~ That doesn't mean owt. ~ It usually does.
他昏了过去。好吗?
He crashed out. OK?
我为约翰感到难过。
I feel sorry for John.
他就像个迷路的…小……
He's like a lost... little...
他60多岁了。
He's in his 60s.
不，他不是!
No, he isn't!
是吗?
Is he?
谢丽尔呢?
What about Cheryl?
你知道谢丽尔!
You know about Cheryl!
她已经离开了。
She's cleared out and gone.
罗比一开始只是和她一起去的
And Robbie only went with her in the first place
因为他反对我做一个…
because he was reacting against me being a...
是一个…吗?
Being a...?
笨蛋。
Twit.
所以你和约翰，一切都结束了?
So you and John - that's all over and done with?
我甚至不再喜欢约翰了。~就像永远?
~ I don't even like John any more. ~ Like forever?
我不确定我是否做过。
I'm not sure I ever did.
~下次见。哦，不，我不讨厌他。
~ Till next time. ~ Well, no, I don't dislike him.
我只是觉得他很傻
I just think he brings out daft
愚蠢的东西在我身上，我不想再那样了。
stupid stuff in me and I don't want to be like that any more.
好吗?
OK?
罗比邀请了我，你知道，你喜欢他，
And Robbie's asked me and - you know - you like him,
我喜欢他。这是显而易见的。
I like him. It's a no-brainer.
哦，那正合你意。
Oh, right up your street, then.
你真有趣!你很机智，也很敏锐。
You're so funny! You're so witty, you're so sharp.
~是的。自从他开始在加里家工作以来，他变得非常自大。
~ Yup. ~ He's got all cocky since he's started working at Gary's.
天知道为什么。这只是一个星期六的工作。
God knows why. It's only a Saturday job.
我不知道。
Cock o' t'midden.
有个叔叔当老板真是太酷了。
It's so cool having an uncle who's the boss.
人们为了表现得好而倾尽全力……对我!
People falling all over themselves being nice... to me!
~粪堆上的公鸡。你给他打电话了吗?
~ Cock o' the dung-hill. ~ Did you ring him?
我什么时候有时间?
When have I had time?
他说给他打电话。
He said to ring him.
我也不想听任何自作聪明的废话
And I don't want to hear any smart-arse shit-stirring
在罗比面前评论约翰。
comments about John in front of Robbie.
对吧?
Right?
你好!
Hiya!
再过一刻钟晚饭就好了。
Supper'll be ready in a quarter of an hour.
太棒了!完美!
Fantastic! Perfect!
我能做点什么吗?摆桌子?
Can I do anything? Set the table?
不，你没事的，亲爱的。我已经做到了。
No, you're all right, love. I've done it.
我们要邀请加里参加我们的婚礼吗?
Are we inviting Gary to t'wedding?
~肯定。~没有。为什么不呢?
~ Sure. ~ No. ~ Why not?
我们为什么不呢?我们不妨。
~ Why aren't we? ~ We might as well.
我想如果你不邀请他，他会有点生气的。
I think he'd be a bit pissed off if you didn't invite him.
哦，亲爱的。我们为什么不邀请他?
~ Oh, dear. ~ Why aren't we inviting him?
我是开玩笑的。
I was joking.
我们当然会邀请他。
Course we're inviting him.
她不喜欢他。她嫉妒他。
She doesn't like him. She's jealous of him.
我为什么要嫉妒他?
Why am I jealous of him?
如此成功和友善。
Being so successful and nice.
是的,不管。
Yeah, whatever.
反正他知道婚礼的事。因为我发短信告诉他了。和爷爷。
He knows about t'wedding, anyway. cos I've texted him and told him. And Grandad.
我想爷爷对你为什么不亲自告诉他有点困惑。
I think Grandad were a bit bemused about how come you'd not told him yourself.
你不喜欢他吗?加里。
Don't you like him? Gary.
我当然喜欢他!
Course I like him!
是啊，那又怎样?summat。
Yeah, but what, then? There's summat.
我不知道。我不知道。
I don't know. I don't know.
我喜欢她。
I like her.
~幸福。~她绕着燃烧的漩涡。
~ Felicity. ~ She's round the flaming twist.
她很有趣。
She's funny.
那么,什么呢?
What, then?
她叹了口气
SHE SIGHS
他是个好人，我爸爸。他犯了一个错误，
He's a good man, me dad. He made a mistake,
他做了不该做的事，但我不能把他钉在十字架上。
he did something he shouldn't have, but I can't crucify him.
加里很棒。多可爱的人啊。我们有多幸运?
And Gary's great. What a lovely man. How lucky are we?
但是…我不晓得。
But... I dunno.
我爸爸对他很着迷
Me dad's so fascinated by him,
就好像他是一个成功的，温文尔雅的，他本该拥有的神童。
like he's the successful, suave, wunderkind he should've always had.
而不是他最后得到的那个没用的笨蛋。
Rather than the feckless knob that he ended up with.
~你爸爸没这么说。他当然没说过。
~ You dad's not said that. ~ Course he's not said it.
所以你也没给你爸发短信吗?
Is that why you didn't text your dad either?
如果这能安慰你的话。我觉得你很完美。
Well, if it's any consolation. I think you're perfect.
我最好给他打个电话。
I'd better ring him.
看看他想要什么。
See what he wants.
~迟了!对不起。~没关系。
~ Late! Sorry. ~ That's OK.
你好吗？
How are you?
我能喝点茶吗?
Can I have some tea?
谢谢你来见我。很高兴见到你。
~ Thanks for meeting me. ~ It's nice to see you.
是吗?
Is it?
为什么不呢?~嗯…
~ Why wouldn't it be? ~ Well...
艾伦已经两周没给我打电话了。
Alan hasn't rung me for two weeks.
他一直在哈罗盖特。~是的。
~ He's been in Harrogate. ~ Yeah.
这一切都很痛苦。适合所有人。
It's all been pretty traumatic. For everyone.
确定。但你也没给我打电话。直到星期天。
Sure. But then you didn't ring me either. Till Sunday.
嗯，我也有点忙不过来了。
Well, I've been a bit snowed under meself as well.
课程。课程。我只是有点多疑。
Course. Course. It's just that I'm paranoid.
是吗?~不正常。
~ Are you? ~ Not normally.
拉夫怎么样了?
How's Raff doing?
很好!他很喜欢。他很棒，是个很好的小伙子。
Really well! He loves it. He's great, he's such a nice lad.
谢谢你！他可以。
Thank you. He can be.
当他不是…自大的小混蛋。
When he's not being a... cocky little dick.
我和费利西蒂最近关系不太好。
Me and Felicity haven't been getting on very well lately.
~真的吗?~对不起，那是……
~ Really? ~ Sorry, that's...
~没有。~我是说…自从这一切发生之后。
~ No. ~ I mean... it's since all this.
所以可能都是我的错。
So it's probably all my fault.
为什么?你是什么意思?
Why? What do you mean?
我突然……
I suddenly...
我感到很生气。
I felt very angry.
那个星期天我们一起吃过午饭之后。
After we'd been over for lunch the other Sunday.
为什么?
Why?
卡洛琳怎么样?
How's Caroline?
她的应对。你为什么生气?
She's coping. Why did you feel angry?
我不知道为什么。
I don't know why.
~这不是…对…生气?
~ It's not... ~ Angry with...?
一切。与…为什么我的父母从来不告诉我。
Everything. With... Why my parents never told me.
你知道，我现在再也不能和他们谈这个话题了。
You know, that's a conversation that I can never have with them now.
是的，我知道。我明白了。我明白。
Yeah, I know. I understand. I do understand.
因为我对……
Because I feel the same about...
我记起了一些事情。过去发生的事情。
And I'm remembering things. Things that happened in the past.
我想知道他们是否更关心我们的亚当——我的兄弟——而不是我。
And I'm wondering whether they did think more about our Adam - my brother - than they did about me.
~他比呃…年轻?~是啊!我爸爸是他爸爸，他真正的爸爸。
~ He's younger than erm...? ~ Yeah! Yeah, and my dad was his dad, his proper dad.
我从来没有，从来没有这样想过。
And I've never, NEVER thought like this before.
我以前从来没有生气或嫉妒过。好吧，不是这样的。
I've never felt angry or jealous before. Well, not like this.
我知道。
I know.
它改变了过去。几乎。尽管事实并非如此。
It changes the past. Almost. Even though it doesn't.
但是，是的。它给过去涂上了色彩。是的，这很难。
But it - yeah. It colours the past. And yeah, that's difficult.
~但是…~那就没人…没人给我打电话。
~ But... ~ Then no-one... nobody rings me up.
在那个星期天之后，
After that Sunday,
所以我脑子里满是关于我亲生父母的事
so I've got all this shit in my head about my real parents,
我在想，“哦，现在他真的不想了解我了”。
and I'm thinking, "Oh, and now he doesn't really want to get to know me".
~不，那是……但是我总是要打电话。
~ No, that's... ~ But I am the one who always has to do the ringing up.
不。加里。诚实。你想得太多了。
No. Gary. Honestly. You're reading too much into it.
这几周很奇怪。
It's been an odd few weeks.
你要结婚了!
You're getting married!
是啊!
Yeah!
你被邀请了!
You are invited!
真的吗?
Really?
如果你担心没有我爸爸的消息，就给他打电话!
Just ring me dad up if you're worried you've not heard from him!
~是的，但是我…~什么?我不敢。
~ Yeah, but I... ~ What? ~ I daren't.
不敢吗?你是加里·杰克逊!
Daren't? You're Gary Jackson!
那不代表什么!
That doesn't mean anything!
我可不想最后总觉得自己是个讨厌鬼!
I don't want to end up feeling like I'm being a nuisance all the time!
我爸爸不会那样想的。
My dad would never think like that.
你的爸爸?
Your dad?
是的。我爸爸，你爸爸。无论什么。
Yeah. My dad, your dad. Whatever.
他对我感兴趣，是吗?
He is interested in me, isn't he?
是的!绝对的!他觉得你很棒!
Yes! Absolutely! He thinks you're fantastic!
西莉亚也喜欢我。
And Celia liked me.
她爱你。~对不起。
~ She loved you. ~ Sorry.
~不要…~我不是这样的。这，这只是…
~ Don't... ~ I'm not like this. This - it's just...
真是太震惊了，吉莉安。和…这就像……
it's just been such a shock, Gillian. And... It's like...
我才刚刚明白过来。正常。所有的…
it's only just sunk in. Properly. All the...
~我知道。~影响。~我知道。我知道。
~ I know. ~ Implications. ~ I know. I do know.
对不起。我——对不起——我被迷住了。
Sorry. I get - sorry - I get obsessed.
还有一些奇怪的事情。这就是我!
And a little bit weird about stuff. That's just me!
她给我端茶来了吗?~冷静点。
~ Is she even bringing me some tea? ~ Calm down.
~是的。是的。是的。是的。~冷静点。
~ Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. ~ Calm down.
我一到家就给你发邮件。
I'm going to e-mail you the second I'm home.
是的。请做。
Yes. Please do.
我要回来过暑假。~好。
~ And I'm going to be back for the summer. ~ Good.
整整两个星期!
For two whole weeks!
我要给你带很多东西!
And I'm going to bring you so much stuff!
然后你和妈妈
And then you and Mom -
这个妈妈要来看我。
this Mom - are going to visit me.
~是的。~没错。
~ We are. ~ That's right.
西莉亚。
Celia.
祝你一路平安。
You have a safe journey.
艾伦。
Alan.
你们俩真是太好了。
You've both been so kind.
你们保持联系。我们两个，还有这两个。
You keep in touch. With us two, as well as these two.
我会的，我当然会。
I will, of course I will.
你还好吧，亲爱的?~是的。
~ Y'all right, love? ~ Yup.
艾略特博士吗?
Dr Elliot?
霍莉?
Holly?
这是…吗?这里是康威路46号。
Is this...? This is 46 Conway Drive.
我在找麦肯齐-道森医生。
I'm looking for a Dr McKenzie-Dawson.
~哦。是的。那就是我。~是吗?
~ Oh. Yes. That's me. ~ Is it?
是的……我，我结婚了。
Yes... I - I got married.
天啊。好。中介派我来的。
Gosh. Well. The agency sent me.
我早到了十分钟，不过如果你愿意，我可以先走了再回来。~不，不，不要那样做。
~ And I'm ten minutes early, but I can go away and come back if you like. ~ No, no, don't do that.
~但是…你去苏塞克斯读社会学。~我退学了!
~ But... you went off to Sussex to read sociology. ~ I dropped out!
那个姓，当中介打来电话的时候……那不是……
The surname - when the agency rang... That wasn't...
~我没有…~我退学了，我也结婚了!
~ I didn't... ~ I dropped out and I got married too!
现在我是保姆了。我从没想过去苏塞克斯。
And now I'm a nanny. I never wanted to go to Sussex.
是我的父母。祝福他们。和你!
It was my parents. Bless them. And you!
对我们所有人来说都是如此雄心勃勃!
So ambitious for us all!
但我真正想做的就是这个。这就是我要做的!
But all I ever really wanted to do was this. And now that's what I am doing!
老实说，我再高兴不过了。
And I couldn't be happier, honestly.
冬青。这是我妈妈。这是我的继父。
Holly. This is my mother. And this is my stepfather.
你好!~西莉亚。
~ How do you do? ~ Celia.
艾伦。你好。
Alan. Hello.
这是弗洛拉。
And this is Flora.
你好,植物!我的天哪，你真漂亮!
Hello, Flora! My goodness me, aren't you pretty?
多漂亮的皮肤啊。
What beautiful skin.
我不是她的生母。
I'm not her biological mother.
做的,嗯…局里跟你解释过我的情况了吗?
Did, erm... did the agency explain my situation to you?
不。不，不完全是。
No. Not - not entirely.
你想喝点茶吗?
Would you like some tea?
我想喝点茶。
I'd love some tea.
~你想进来吗?~谢谢。
~ Do you want to come inside? ~ Thank you.
多漂亮的房子啊!
What a gorgeous house!
天哪，看看这些虹膜。
Gosh, look at those irises.
那绝对是我最喜欢的颜色。
That's my absolute number one favourite colour.
哇。那是你的车吗?
Wow. Is that your car?
不,这是……
No, it's...
真的吗?好样的!
Really? Good for you!
如果我可以选择一辆车，我想我会选那辆。认真对待。
If I could choose a car, I think I'd choose that one. Seriously.
除了我不敢开它。我想我还是看着它吧。
Except I'd be scared to drive it. I think I'd just rather look at it.
天啊，这走廊真漂亮……
Gosh, it's a nice hallway...
今天我们可能会去克纳斯伯勒野餐。
Today we might take a picnic to Knaresborough.
我们刚接到布拉德福德警方的电话。
We've just had a phone call from the police in Bradford.
~他们抓走了弗洛拉。警察抓了弗洛拉?
~ They've got Flora. ~ The police've got Flora?
我告诉过你我不想要孩子。
I told you I didn't want a baby.
我说过我不想要孩子。
I said I didn't want a baby.
我在撒谎。说我从没告诉过任何人。
I'm lying. Saying I never told anyone.
劳伦斯，这是格雷格。~你好。
~ Lawrence, this is Greg. ~ Hi.
再见。
Bye.
凯特去世还不到六周。
It's less than six weeks since Kate died.
~好。你真的在问我这个问题吗?
~ Well. ~ Are you seriously asking me that question?
还有一件事……你会误解我的意思的。
Then the other thing... Oh, you're going to take this the wrong way.